Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, פורים שמח. Purim Sameach. Today's דף daf
is ל"א. Lamed Aleph. And we pick up in the middle of
ל"א, Lamed Aleph, עמוד א'. Amud Aleph. And we pick up with,
where are we?
גופא. Gufa. It is about ten lines before the lines get wide.
גופא. Gufa. So middle of the line.
Starts with the word לא
הכי מתנינא הדא לה. lo hachi matnina hadola. Okay, גופא. Gufa. So
now we have spoken about, we've introduced this idea that קים ליה
Kimlei and as was correctly pointed out, the phrase קים ליה Kimlei
hasn't even appeared yet, but this concept that if somebody does something
that's חייב מיתת בית דין, chayav misat Beis Din, deserving of execution,
or according to רבי נחוניא בן הקנה Rabbi Nechunia ben HaKanah even
כרת, kares, then that overrides any monetary payment or fine that occurs
at the same time, that is incurred in the process. But the
question is, what's the sense of overlap? So we started with cases
where it was one action that led to both, burning down a
pile of hay on ראש השנה... Rosh Hashanah... on שבת Shabbos or
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But now we dealt with issues that were
two separate acts, but maybe occurred sequentially or at the same time.
So we had an extreme version of that that said all that
matters is the timing. So you could be eating חלב chelev and
destroying with your mouth and destroying property with your feet. And since
it's at the same time, it overrides. So that's a complete shift
of that focus. Now we're back to the idea of thinking it
as during the same act and at different points of time, but
seeing it as a process. And therefore, if it occurs sometime during
that process that's defined the act of the עבירה, aveira, the act
that makes the person deserving of this death penalty, any damage done,
any penalty incurred, monetary fine or obligation incurred, would be overridden, would
not be liable. So that's the context we're dealing with, and the
גמרא Gemara therefore picks up with this right now. גופא. Gufa. Okay,
so אמר רבי אבין, Amar Rabbi Avin,
said
רבי אבין, Rabbi Avin, הזורק חץ מתחלת ארבע לסוף ארבע, hazorek chetz
mit-techilas arba l'sof arba, so somebody shoots an arrow from the beginning
of four אמות amos in רשות הרבים reshus harabim to the end,
וקרע שיראין בהליכתו, v'keria shirayin b'halichaso, and it tore some nice silk
garments in its way, פטור. patur.
He is exempt. Even though the violation of שבת Shabbos only occurred
when the arrow reached the end of its trajectory, actually landed on
the ground, but nevertheless, שעקירה לצורך הנחה היא, she-akira tzarach hanacha hi,
because the picking up of the arrow is necessary for the putting
down. Which the גמרא Gemara before said you might want to interpret
that in certain physical ways, like you can't retrieve the arrow in
mid-flight, so it's all part of the same process. But what actually
seems to make more sense is that he's saying a halachic point.
The act of carrying is defined from the very beginning of the
process. You don't carry by putting something down in רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. You carry by picking it up, traversing רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
and then putting it down. So the very beginning of the process
and the very from the very picking up the arrow to its
traversing, to its going down, is all the act of carrying. And
therefore, even though the liability is incurred at the end, it's all
the act of carrying, so any damage that's occurred during that process
or during that act, one is exempt from. Makes an enormous amount
of sense, focusing in terms of the halachic definition of the sin,
not in terms of the physical activity, although you could focus on
that as well.
Can I just ask a question? פטור patur here refers to the
נזק? nezek?
פטור patur from, correct, from monetary damages.
But he's still
חייב chayav for חילול שבת. chillul Shabbos.
Absolutely. Even though he physically did not put it down himself?
Well, doesn't matter. He shot it and it was gonna land. Now,
if he shot it in a way that, I'm sorry, I'm just
getting my coffee here, in
a way it goes into the trunk of a tree more than
ten...
Right. So when we're...
right. So when you learn הלכות שבת, Hilchos Shabbos, I'm sorry for
being absent here, when you learn הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos or whatever,
מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbos, you find out about what happens if you
try to shoot it to land one place and it lands in
another place or whatever. That's not our concern right now. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. מתיב רבי ביבי בר אביי, Masvei
Rabbi Bibi bar Abaye, so רבי ביבי בר אביי Rabbi Bibi bar
Abaye asked, הגונב כיס בשבת חייב שכבר נתחייב בגניבה קודם שיבא לידי
איסור סקילה. hagonev kis b'Shabbos chayav, she-kvar nischayav b'geneiva kodem she-yavo lidei
issur sekila. If somebody steals a wallet on שבת, Shabbos, they are
still liable to pay for the wallet, because you became obligated in
this act of גניבה geneiva before you did the violation of שבת.
Shabbos. But the moment you picked it up, you stole, and you
only violated שבת Shabbos when you carried it four אמות amos or
you took it from the רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, which is probably
where it was, from the owner's home, to a רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim. Okay, so that's fine. That's completely consistent. הא אם מגרר ויוצא
מגרר ויוצא פטור שהרי איסור שבת וגניבה באים כאחד. Ha im megorer
v'yotzei, megorer v'yotzei, patur, she-harei issur Shabbos u-geneiva ba'im k'echad. If the
person, however, was dragging it and going, dragging it and going,
then you're פטור patur because the violation of שבת Shabbos and the
violation of גניבה geneiva come at the same time. What does that
mean? It means the following. Imagine that, okay, this here, imagine that
this book, this black book here, right, is...
that this is... is my רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and here's my
wallet in my רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
Is that a pocketbook?
No, no, it's not a pocketbook. This is actually my front yard.
Oh the other. This, this is my wallet. Right. This is my
front yard, okay, and over here is the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
So here I am, I'm dragging it, dragging it, dragging it. I
haven't stolen it yet, right? Because you only steal something, the general
assumption is that you only steal something when you do a type
of an act that is similar that is the type of act
that would be how you would transfer property if you were legitimately
selling it to me. So picking it up, taking it into my
domain, the types of ways in which you're קונה, koneh, you do
an act of קנין, kinyan, acquisition of property, only when you do
that act is it considered to have been that you stole the
object, okay? So if I picked it up in your domain, then
that was הגבהה, hagba'ah, then I stole it already, and then only
when I walk out to רשות הרבים reshus harabbim have I violated
שבת, Shabbos, so they're distinct acts, okay? But if I am dragging
it, I haven't stolen it yet because I haven't picked it up.
Then I walk, I go over the line from your רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid into, now the question is into where? because you're only
חייב chayav שבת Shabbos when you go into רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
okay? Then I have violated שבת Shabbos when it went over this
line and the גמרא Gemara also assumes that that's also an act
of קנין kinyan and that's also the act of גניבה. geneiva. Now
that's strange, we'll get to that, because I haven't taken it into
my domain, I've taken it into רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, but maybe
for גניבה geneiva you don't need exactly a normal קנין, kinyan, maybe
it's enough to just take it out of the owner's control even
if you haven't taken it into yours. So now we're going to
assume, this is what most of the גמרא Gemara today is going
to discuss, but if you're doing it like this, then you haven't
stolen it yet and when you do the act of violating שבת,
Shabbos, that's the moment you stole it as well and therefore you're,
you're exempt from payment.
Yours, when you say your personal space? What?
Yours the גנב'ס. ganav's.
What would be your space? Okay well certainly your own property, but
maybe even a type of a space that is that is more
of a neutral space, not a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, but something
that's a semi-private space where you can be seen as having some
degree of control over the space, as opposed to...
like walking into a Starbucks? Would that be considered some kind of
idea?
No, no, it would not be a Starbucks.
It would be... well maybe a Starbucks, actually I shouldn't say that
because a Starbucks is like it's not as it's not as...
there's a space called a סמטא, simta, which is like an alleyway,
which is a place where people have... they're not like, you know,
the mass of people, so they can actually stake out their own
little space in there. So I guess it depends how crowded the
Starbucks is.
A different coffee shop, not Starbucks, where you could actually get a
table and you don't have to wait, okay, anyway fine. But something
like that. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, היה מגרר ויוצא מגרר ויוצא פטור שהרי איסור שבת ואיסור סקילה
באים כאחד, Haya megarrer veyotzei megarrer veyotzei patur sheharei issur Shabbos ve'issur
sekila baim ke'echad,
because then they come at the same time. All right, ואמאי, Ve'amai,
why is it? הכא נמי לימא הגבהה
לצורך הנחה היא. Hacha nami leima hagba'ah letzoirech hanacha hi. Now
it's again, it's a similar type of a question we asked before,
but here you understand it's actually
it's a good question because when you picked it up and then
walked out of the guy's רשות, reshus, okay, so it says wait
a minute, that's exactly the arrow case, right? Because when you pick
it up and walk out of the רשות reshus and then you
put it down in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, the picking of the
up, which which was the stealing, was the beginning of the process
of carrying, right? Is that clear everybody? That's just like the arrow
case. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהגביה על
מנת להצניעו. Hacha bemai askinan kegon shehigbiha al menas lehatznio.
You picked it up, you were not planning on going out to
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. You picked it up and you intended to
steal it, but you thought you were going to hide it, let's
say you figured you'll hide it somewhere else in the house and
you'll take it away when the owner isn't looking. Okay, so you
didn't pick it up with the intent to carry it out to
the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. ונמלך עליו והוציאו, Venimloch alav vehotzio, and
you then you change your mind and you took it out. So
how does that solve it? Because it says the act of picking
it up was the act of גניבה, geneiva, but it wasn't the
beginning of the act of carrying because to begin the act of
carrying when you pick it up you have to intend to carry
it out, right? Is that clear? Yeah. So therefore when you picked
it up and you planned to rehide it in the house, that
was a גניבה geneiva without an intent of of carrying, without a
beginning of a process of carrying. Then it assumes you change your
mind and then you say oh no, I am actually going to
go out to רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, at that moment that's when
the act of carrying begins. Okay, so it it separated those two
processes.
Yeah but you know what's the problem? This is a מלאכה שאינה
מתכוון melacha she'eina miskavein because when he first picked it up he
need the הגבהה, hagba'ah, he had no intent to bring it out.
Right, so what it's assuming is is that when you pick it
up I have I've now stolen it but I've not yet begun
carrying it because I plan on hiding it somewhere in the house.
And then I'm walking around and I'm looking for a place to
hide it and say you know what, I don't have a place
to hide it, I'm just going to go out to רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. At this moment that I plan to go out to
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, now I'm beginning to do the act of
of carrying. Yeah but you've already stolen it.
I get I get you've already stolen it, but
but when
I am מחייב mechayiv at this moment I begin to plan I'm
planning to go out.
Yeah, but there's no הגבהה. hagba'ah.
Oh, so that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, where's
the הגבהה hagba'ah in that case. Okay, where's the עקירה? akirah? Very
good. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, והאי גוונא מי חייב?
ve-hai gavna mi-chayav? It's not כהאי גוונא, ke-hai gavna, it's because there's
no עקירה. akirah.
In such a case, right, right,
in such a case, how are you חייב? chayav? And אמר רב
סיסי, amar Rav Sisi, in the absence of Michael, you're filling his
role here, anticipating the גמרא's Gemara next question. ואמר רב סימון אמר
רבי אבא אמר רבי יוחנן,
ve-amar Rav Simon amar Rabbi Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan, המפנה חפצים מזוית לזוית, ha-mifaneh chafatzim mi-zavit le-zavit, if somebody
is clearing out objects from one corner to another corner ונמלך עליהם
והוציאן, ve-nimlach aleihem ve-hotzi'an, and then he's not planning on taking them
out
to רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, he's just moving things around his house,
and then as he's moving things around he says, I think I'll
bring this out to the street. פטור, patur, you're exempt, שלא הייתה
עקירה משעה ראשונה לכך. she-lo hayetah akirah mi-sha'ah rishonah le-kach. You never,
when you picked it up, you didn't intend to bring it out,
and when you intended to bring it out, you didn't pick it
up. So therefore there's no עקירה. akirah. So here too, if you
picked up the wallet, you did the stealing, but you haven't begun
the act of carrying. When you plan to then take it out,
then you haven't done a picking up. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא תימא לצנעא, lo teima li-tzna, fine, let's forget that case. It's
not that you planned to hide it somewhere else in the house.
אלא אימא על מנת להוציא. ela eima al menat le-hotzi. Fine, you
picked it up, you plan to take it out to רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. So why isn't there for
the act of stealing the same as the beginning of the process
of carrying? דהכא במאי עסקינן, de-hacha be-mai askinan, what are we talking
about?
כשעמד. keshe-amad. So here's the case. A much simpler case. I steal
your wallet and now I say... I'm in your house and I
stole your wallet and I'm saying, okay, I'm going to take it
out to רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, but then before I get a
chance, you say, hey, where you going? I say, oh, nowhere.
So anyway, no, but so I pick it up, I'm sorry, I'm
getting a little bit too much into the Purim spirit. Anyway, I
take it up, I planned to take it out or I don't
plan, it really doesn't matter, but I pick it up to steal
it, I stole it. Then I stop. And I'm stopped here and
I'm waiting here and I'm deciding, I'm going to pause for a
moment, I'm not thinking anymore right now about taking it out, and
then I'm ready to take it out and I go and I
take it out. So when I... after having stopped, it's like I
put it down on the
ground for Shabbat purposes. And then now that I plan to go
and take it out, now it's actually an act of carrying. So
basically where you have the עקירה, akirah, you have the עקירה akirah
because he picked it up to steal it. That was the act
of stealing. Then
he stopped, in the guy's house, he actually stopped moving, he planned
to rest for a moment. And then when you lift your foot
up, exactly. When you're stationary in a place, it's like the object
is on the ground. It settled in the רשות. reshus. Now when
you move, right, עקירת גופו כעקירת חפץ, akirat gufo ke-akirat chafetz, exactly.
Now that you move, that's the moving of the object from its
settled position. So basically we made it into two steps.
Ah, step, very good.
Ah, okay. Anyway, and I forgot to move the thing here. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא אימא על מנת להוציא,
ela eima al menat le-hotzi, והכא
במאי עסקינן כשעמד. ve-hacha be-mai askinan keshe-amad.
You stood. עמד למאי? amad le-mai? For
what purpose did you stand and pause? אי לכתף, ei le-chateif, if
it's to move it from one shoulder to the next, that's what
the word לכתף, le-chateif, a shoulder means. So it's basically to
adjust yourself or a normal type of a way to... I got
to readjust my packages. So אורחיה הוא. orcheih hu. That's normal. That's
not considered a stop. That doesn't end one process and begin the
next. If you're walking and you're stopping at the light and you're
waiting for the light to change or you're adjusting your packages, it
doesn't end the process.
But when you're walking, you stop every time...
Well, don't worry, the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that. אלא
בעומד לפוש. ela be-omed la-fush. You're taking a pause in order to
take a rest. So you're actually not still in the process. Wait
a minute, I got to rest for a few minutes,
or maybe even changed your mind and then you change your mind
again. So if it's in the process and you're just pausing momentarily
to adjust things or for necessary things, that's not an interruption. But
if you actually paused for the sake of resting or some other
type of a break, then it is. And then we have two
processes that are going on here. The first one you stole it,
the second one you carried.
That word לפוש. la-fush. It's like he stops and goes...
right, there you go. אבל לכתף מאי? aval le-chateif mai?
So what are you telling me though? That would make it two
processes. But if he actually stopped in order to just adjust his
packages, what would be the story? Then it would be... excuse me,
I missed turning the page. פטור, patur, you say he's exempt, because
then it's all... the stealing is part of the process of carrying.
So if that's true, עד דתני היה מגרר ויוצא מגרר ויוצא פטור.
ad de-tani hayah megareir ve-yotze megareir ve-yotze patur. If it wanted to
shift and tell you here's a way in which it happens at
the same time, when you're dragging it out and you cross the
line at the same time you steal it, the line from רשות
היחיד reshus ha-yachid to the רשות הרבים. reshus ha-rabbim. So if that's
true, why do you have to give such a weird case? נפלוג
וניתני בדידיה. niflog ve-nisni be-dideih. Tell me a more simple case
and maybe a case that even has a bigger חידוש. chiddush. במה
דברים אמורים, ba-meh devarim amurim, when is it when you pick it
up and walk it out of the house you're exempt? בעומד לפוש,
be-omed la-fush, if you stood and took a break between the two
processes. אבל לכתף, aval le-chateif, but if you just stopped to adjust
the package or you didn't take a break at all, פטור, patur,
you'd be exempt. So it does not sound like that. says the
גמרא, Gemara, because if you have to create a crazy scenario, not
so crazy, but anyway, if you have to read in some special
scenario in order to say why you're exempt, it should have just
given me a simple scenario why you're חייב, chayav, it should have
given me a simple scenario why you're פטור. patur. You're פטור patur
because in a case where you picked it up and walked straight
out of the house, right?
So I mean you understand the force of the גמרא's Gemara question.
Why do you need—I am such a—being such a כלוץ klutz today—why
do you need to be doing this crazy case of like dragging
to whatever, if a normal case of picking it up, walking straight
out of the house, and putting it down you're also פטור, patur,
right? Because the process begins from the time you pick it up.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, let
us use this phrase, נפלוג ונתני בדידיה. Niflog venisni bedidei. What does
נפלוג ונתני—what Niflog venisni does נפלוג Niflog mean?
Let us make the distinction within the case itself. Like like a
מפלוג, miflog, right? פלג Plag is half whatever.
Why do you have to bring a completely different case? Make a
distinction within this case itself. If it wasn't a case of pausing
in the middle, then you'd be פטור. patur. Okay.
אלא, Ella, says
the גמרא, Gemara, fine, you've got a really good point because this
ברייתא braisa really makes it sound like you would never be פטור
patur in a case where you normally picked it up, right? So
why not?
So therefore so then yeah, that challenges the idea of the arrow
case. אלא הא מני, Ella ha mani, who is this? בן עזאי
היא, Ben Azzai hi, it's בן עזאי. Ben Azzai. דאמר מהלך כעומד
דמי, Deamar mehalach keomed dami, right? This is what Dov was saying,
that בן עזאי Ben Azzai says walking is like standing. Okay, meaning
every time you walk, you pause, right? Your foot goes down, so
that's a momentary stop and then you so try telling that to
the officer when you didn't stop at the stop sign. Well, you
know, every microsecond the car was in its place for a microsecond.
Anyway, it's sort of like Zeno's paradox.
Right, anyway. Exactly, you'll never get there because it always has to
traverse half the distance. So anyway.
There you go. So so this is the idea that walking is
like stopping. So therefore you are only חייב, chayav, the logic of
this therefore is the act of עקירה akira from going to רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim to רשות היחיד reshus hayachid only is that moment
before you step over the line, right? If I pick up the
object and I walk three steps, each of these was a mini
a mini הנחה. hanacha. Okay, so the only act that I can
be חייב chayav is when I actually go over the line. So
that's the one step that I did and that is an עקירה
akira and an הנחה hanacha without a minute in between between רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim and רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Okay, now of course
the question is, so what do you do, that's fine when all
you have to do is make one step over one line. But
what do you have to do about walking ארבע אמות arba amos
in רשות הרבים? reshus harabbim? How do you ever get it since
every step you make you stopped, right? Unless you're like the Jolly
Green Giant and you can take one step that's ארבע אמות. arba
amos. So what do you do? So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi asks the
question and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says well, maybe it's he jumped. So
it would actually say that according to בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, you
wouldn't be חייב chayav for walking ארבע אמות, arba amos, you'd only
be חייב chayav if you actually jumped the
ארבע אמות. arba amos.
Okay, now the other possibility is is that, you know, okay, for
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim for the ארבע אמות arba amos thing there's
no alternative so we have to say you're חייב chayav for walking.
But for the רשות הרבים reshus harabbim רשות היחיד reshus hayachid thing,
there you're only it's only that last step that goes over the
line that's considered the act.
So I want to know what רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yermiya would say
if one foot is outside on the other side.
Exactly, yes, exactly. All right, so anyway, yes, that is the classic
רבי ירמיה. Rebbi Yermiya. All right, so everyone.
So so we have so that's the reason. The reason the ברייתא
braisa assumes that you'll never have them coming at the same time
is an assumption that meaning if I didn't quote בן עזאי Ben
Azzai and if I just reframed it the following way, is the
assumption that the act of carrying from רשות הרבים reshus harabbim to
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid only is only that act of the going
over of the line, that the actual step that's going from before
the line is the act of עקירה akira and the step when
it goes over the line is the act of הנחה. hanacha. So
therefore the only way you get a stealing and a carrying coming
at the same time is the case of dragging, because any other
case you would have considered what the stealing that it would have
been considered to be a distinct act from the act of carrying.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, אבל זורק מאי, Aval
zorek mai, but what would you say according to Ben according to
this? But let's say he actually didn't walk it out of the
house, let's say he took the wallet and he threw it out
of the house. So what would you say? Then you'd say פטור,
patur, then you'd also say he'd be exempt, right? Because you don't
have this idea of like little mini-stops along the way and and
then the picking up that's like the threw the shooting of the
arrow. So if that's true, we're back to our question: נפלוג ונתני
בדידיה. Niflog venisni bedidei. Still, why did you need this crazy case
of dragging? Why not say במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when
is it true that picking up your wallet and walking it out
you're חייב? chayav? דמהלך, Dimehalach, if you're walking. אבל זורק, Aval zorek,
but if you threw it out of the house, פטור, patur, you're
exempt. Now, that's not such a good question because switching it from
walking it out of the house to throwing it out of the
house, I'm not sure if the case of throwing it is so
much different than a case of dragging it out of the house.
So the גמרא Gemara so so the גמרא Gemara basically says מגרר
דייקא איצטריכא ליה. Megarer deika itztaricha lei.
No, the case of dragging was a was one that it really
wanted to teach. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka dachatach amina, I would have
thought to say אין דרך הוצאה בכך, Ein derech hotza'ah bekach, maybe
dragging you'd be פטור patur for שבת Shabbos because normally people don't
carry a wallet. out by dragging it along the ground. קא משמע
לן Ka mashma lan that you're even that you're חייב Chayav for
שבת. Shabbos. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask well
why is that? It is really a שינוי, Shinui, it is a
strange way to carry and you should be exempt. ובימאי? U'vimai? What's
the case? אי ברברבי, Ei b'ravrevi,
if it was a big wallet, so maybe it wasn't a wallet,
if it was a knapsack let's say, a heavy knapsack, right, okay,
אורחיהו, Orcheihu, that would be a normal thing to drag it on
the ground depending on how heavy it was. אי בזוטרי, Ei b'zutrei,
if it was a small little money bag, לאו אורחיה, Lav orcheih,
then you really should be exempt. So either it's obvious or it's
not or it's not true. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא במציעי.
Ela b'mitziei. Okay, so it's like a middle-sized thing where it's not
so normal to carry it by שלעפינג shlepping it but it's normal
enough. And since it's normal enough, therefore it's not a שינוי Shinui
and you're going to be חייב Chayav for חילול שבת Chillul Shabbos
and therefore you're going to be exempt. So basically we're saying the
simple sense of this ברייתא, Braisa, let's be honest, is against the
idea of the shooting of the arrow. Says that the beginning of
the process does not get you exempt, it has to be literally
that exact moment. But the גמרא Gemara in order to reconcile it
with the position of the shooting of the arrow that if it's
somewhere during the process you're exempt, has to explain that the reason
it's not during the process in the case of the picking it
up and walking it out is either because you paused in the
middle or because it's בן עזאי Ben Azzai that sees that the
process only begins the moment before you step outside of the door.
Okay, and therefore a case where it is, right, and therefore a
case where it is during the process would either be a case
of throwing it out or would be a case of dragging it.
Throwing it out has the חידוש Chiddush that the act of stealing
started before, dragging it has the חידוש Chiddush that it's considered a
type enough of a הוצאה Hotza'a to be חייב Chayav for שבת.
Shabbos. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now we're
still not done because now we get to the question I asked
you before: where did you drag it to? Okay, so let's take
a look. ודאפקיה להיכא? U'd'afkeih l'heicha? Where did you drag it to?
אי דאפקיה לרשות הרבים, Ei d'afkeih l'reshus harabbim, if you dragged it
out of the guy's house straight into the public domain, the major
street, איסור שבת איכא, Issur Shabbos ika, that violation of שבת, Shabbos,
רשות היחיד לרשות הרבים, Reshus hayachid l'reshus harabbim, איסור גניבה ליכא, Issur
geneiva leika, but there's not an idea of stealing. Because here's the
problem: in order to steal it, presumably we have to do a
normal act of קנין. Kinyan. A normal act of קנין Kinyan is
taking it out of your control and putting it into mine. Now
I can do that if I'm on your property by lifting it
up. But the whole point is I didn't lift it up. So
I can do it, so the only way I can do it
is taking it out if I'm not lifting it up is taking
it out of your property into either my personal property, my yard,
or into some space that I have some mini control over like
some side street that at least I can have some control over
my immediate space. But not into the public domain. And שבת, Shabbos,
the only way you're חייב Chayav on שבת Shabbos is from the
private domain to the public domain, to the major thoroughfare. So they
seem to be mutually exclusive: when you get an איסור שבת, Issur
Shabbos, I can't be considered taking it into my רשות Reshus מידי
גנב, midei ganav, and when I am considered taking it into my
רשות, Reshus, you don't have a רשות הרבים. Reshus harabbim. So that's
the גמרא's Gemara's question. Okay, אי דאפקיה לרשות הרבים, Ei d'afkeih l'reshus
harabbim, if you took it into the major thoroughfare, איסור שבת איכא,
Issur Shabbos ika, איסור גניבה ליכא, Issur geneiva leika, you have the
violation of שבת Shabbos but you don't have the stealing. אי דאפקיה
לרשות היחיד, Ei d'afkeih l'reshus hayachid, if you brought it into let's
say my own yard, my private domain, איסור גניבה איכא, Issur geneiva
ika, you have stealing, איסור שבת ליכא, Issur Shabbos leika, but you
don't have שבת. Shabbos. So it says look, צריכה, Tzricha, here's the
case:
you went from one רשות היחיד Reshus hayachid to another רשות היחיד.
Reshus hayachid. Right, our yards are right next to each other.
Exactly. So then obviously there's no
חילול שבת. Chillul Shabbos. לא צריכה דאפקיה לצדי רשות הרבים. Lo tzricha
d'afkeih l'tzidei reshus harabbim. You brought it on let's say the sidewalks,
the edges of רשות הרבים.
Reshus
harabbim.
Okay, כמאן? K'man? Well let's take a look. So how are you
considering the sides of רשות הרבים? Reshus harabbim? אי כרבי אליעזר, Ei
k'Rabbi Eliezer, and a sidewalk is an exactly good example because a
sidewalk is like a separate like raised space, but anyway, you know,
I don't know, maybe a good example would be, you know what
a good example would be, would be like the
what's those things they have on the highway, the, you know, the
shoulders, right, you know, when there's like a shoulder of the highway
type of a thing where you might go over and you might
want to pull over or something but it's obviously not the main
thoroughfare. רש"י Rashi also points out that there would be some type
of like pistons, he doesn't say pistons, what are those things called,
those barricades, no, not barricades, what are those plastic things they put
up in the construction, the
anyway, whatever, cones. Anyway, no, but רש"י Rashi don't say cones. But
anyway, רש"י Rashi says there would be some type of obstruction so
you wouldn't easily go from one to the next.
So if you want a contemporary translation, rumble strip. Exactly. So you
have a highway, you got the rumble strip and then you got
the sides of the highway.
Okay. צדי רשות הרבים. Tzidei reshus harabbim. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Now כמאן? K'man? Who is it going like?
אי כרבי אליעזר דאמר צדי רשות הרבים כרשות הרבים דאמי, Ei k'Rabbi
Eliezer d'amar tzidei reshus harabbim k'reshus harabbim dami, if it's like Rabbi
Eliezer who says those sides of the public thoroughfare count as the
public thoroughfare, then we're all going to be back to the same
question. So then איסור שבת איכא אישתכח, Issur Shabbos ika ishtakach, so
then you have it that it's רשות הרבים Reshus harabbim and you've
violated שבת Shabbos but איסור גניבה ליכא, Issur geneiva leika, but you
don't have stealing because it's רשות הרבים. Reshus harabbim. ואי אמרת, Ve'ei
amrat, if you say the reverse: אי כרבנן דאמרי צדי רשות הרבים
לאו כרשות הרבים דאמי, Ei k'rabbanan d'amri tzidei reshus harabbim lav k'reshus
harabbim dami,
if it's like the Rabbis that say the sides are not like
the רשות הרבים, Reshus harabbim, so איסור גניבה איכא, Issur geneiva ika,
it could be like גניבה, geneiva, it's not רשות הרבים, Reshus harabbim,
it's enough of a space that I have some private control over,
so So therefore it's enough to do גניבה gneiva into that place,
but איסור שבת ליכא, isur Shabbos leka, but it's not רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם כרבי אליעזר. l'olam k'Rabbi
Eliezer. No, it's like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's not רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim.
I'm sorry, that it is רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. וכי אמר רבי
אליעזר צידי רשות הרבים כרשות הרבים דמי? v'chi amar Rabbi Eliezer tziddei
reshus harabim k'reshus harabim dami? For what purposes does he say the
sides count as רשות הרבים? reshus harabim? הני מילי
לחיובא דשבת. hani mili l'chiyuva d'Shabbos. That's when it's enough of a
רשות הרבים reshus harabim to be for purposes of violating שבת. Shabbos.
דזימנין דדחקי רבים ואתו להתם. d'zimnin d'dachki rabim v'asu l'hatam. Sometimes the
mass, you know,
there's
too many people going through the thoroughfare and they use the shoulders.
Okay, so therefore it's enough of a space that's accessible to the
רבים rabim and connected enough to the main thoroughfare that it counts
for רשות הרבים reshus harabim for שבת Shabbos purposes. אבל לעניין מקנה,
aval l'inyan mikna, but if you want to use that space to
acquire things, to take possession of something, קניא kanya you
can. מאי טעמא? mai taama? דלא שכיחי רבים. d'la shechichi rabim. Because
most of the time the רבים rabim aren't there. So it's an
interesting middle space. Okay? Is it enough of a space that I
can be considered to have some control over the space I'm in?
Yes, because it's not generally overrun with the רבים. rabim. Most of
the time it's quiet, and if I'm here, nobody else is bothering
me. Okay? So I can, if I take something into here, then
I actually do take possession of it. On the other hand, because
it's connected to רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, and there are times that
it's used by the רבים, rabim, that's enough to make it considered
part of the רשות הרבים reshus harabim for שבת Shabbos purposes. So
you have a space that works for חילול שבת chilul Shabbos and
for taking possession, and that's where you drag it into.
So let's imagine our case is that we took the wallet out
from somebody's house,
I'm dragging the wallet out
from
your house and I'm going to be מחלל שבת m'chalel Shabbos the
moment it goes out of your house into רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
But I also have to do גניבה gneiva the moment it goes
into רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So where was that גניבה? gneiva?
So I have to be within the ארבע אמות arba amos of
רשות הרבים reshus harabim though?
No, רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to רשות הרבים reshus harabim we're doing,
not the ארבע אמות. arba amos. So that moment is going to
צידי רשות הרבים, tziddei reshus harabim, which I have enough control over
that it's good for a קניין, kinyan, but it's connected to רשות
הרבים reshus harabim so therefore it's a חילול שבת chilul Shabbos from
going from your house.
We don't have to worry about you having stopped in the middle,
right?
When we're not worrying with the stop.
We just dragged it all the way. Right, exactly. The way רש"י
Rashi calls צידי tziddei here is a סימטא. simta. He uses the
same language often. Okay, so something not too big, something not too
small.
Exactly, it's just right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
רב אשי אמר. Rav Ashi amar. Now רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi
amar, so that seems like a perfect answer. רב אשי אמר כגון
שצירף ידו למטה משלושה וקיבלו. Rav Ashi amar k'gon shetziref yado l'mata
mishlosha v'kiblo. Basically what you did was, no, you did a קניין
kinyan called a קניין יד. kinyan yad. A קניין יד kinyan yad
is if something's on my person, in my hand or anywhere on
my person, then that's like being in my yard. Okay, it's better
than being in my yard, it's on my person. If I can
own something by being in my property by being in my yard,
I can own something by being on my person. So what I'm
doing here is,
I need two hands here, hold this up. I am dragging, I'm
dragging it out of your house and then when I get to
the רשות הרבים reshus harabim I go like this. So I was
מחלל שבת m'chalel Shabbos because it was in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
landed in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, but I was קונה koneh it
because it landed in רשות הרבים reshus harabim in my hand. And
if it's in my hand, I'm קונה koneh it. So that's actually
a simple answer. It says when I'm doing this, I'm not fully
on my person, I'm just holding onto it, right? But it's not
like fully on my person. This is fully on my person. I'm
not קונה koneh it like this, because I'm just holding onto a
part of it, okay, and I'm dragging it. But when at the
moment when I transfer the line, I catch it in my hand.
Oh, we want to make you חייב chayav for both of these
cases? we don't want to make you חייב chayav for just one?
No, we want to make you do both at the same moment.
And that's why we're saying וקיבלו. v'kiblo. Oh, we're saying, okay. So
at this moment I catch it in my hand and therefore now
that it's fully on my person as opposed to this, I'm קונה
koneh it. And it doesn't matter where I'm standing, even if I'm
in רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay?
So therefore at that moment it's both חילול שבת chilul Shabbos and
גניבה gneiva coming at the same time. Now,
why does the גמרא Gemara say that my hand is under three
טפחים? tfachim? So רש"י Rashi says, it's a whole רש"י תוספות, Rashi
Tosafot, but רש"י Rashi basically says because if I were to have
lifted it up higher than three טפחים tfachim in order to put
it in my hand, dragging dragging dragging and then I'm going to
go like this, then as soon as I lift it up higher
than three טפחים tfachim I've done הגבהה. hagbaha. So I'm קונה koneh
it before חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. Okay? But if I keep it
under three טפחים, tfachim, I haven't done הגבהה hagbaha and the moment
that I'm קונה koneh it is also the moment I've done חילול
שבת. chilul Shabbos. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. וכדרבא,
u'kh'de'Rava, like רבא. Rava.
דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava, like רבא Rava because רבא Rava says, ידו
של אדם חשובה לו כארבע על ארבע. yado shel adam chashuva lo
k'arba al arba. A person's hand counts as four by four טפחים
tfachim for that if it's in your hand it's like you put
it down on the ground for שבת Shabbos purposes. So therefore it's
in your hand, so it's like it's on the ground for שבת
Shabbos purposes and it's also in your hand and therefore you own
it even though you're in a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay? So
that's a nice answer too. You caught it in your hand so
you can own it in a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. There's another
way of reading רבא Rava but we're not going to worry about
it right now. רב אחא מתני הכי. Rav Aha masni hachi. רב
אחא Rav Aha teaches it the way we taught, some of one
of these answers above, either צידי רשות הרבים... tziddei reshus harabim... or
catching it in your hand. רבינא מתני לעולם דאפקיה לרשות הרבים. Ravina
masni l'olam d'afkey l'reshous harabbim. And רבינא Ravina has a more radical
position. We don't need some special answer: caught it in your hand,
צידי רשות הרבים. tziddey reshous harabbim. No. You took it out of
the guy's house straight into רשות הרבים. reshous harabbim. Okay? וברשות הרבים
נמי קני. u'v'reshous harabbim nami kana.
And actually, you can actually take possession of something even in a
רשות הרבים, reshous harabbim, against everything we've assumed. ותרייהו בדיוקא דהמתניתין קמיפלגי.
v'trayehu b'diyuka d'hamasnisen kamifligi.
And they debate how to how to read like a you know
in like a what to derive from the language of the following
משנה. mishna. דתנן, detnan, because we taught in a משנה: mishna: היה
מושכו ויוצא. haya moshcho ve'yotze. So this is a guy I'm coming
into your property and I'm stealing your cow. And I'm dragging it
out of your property, ומת. u'meis. And then it dies. So basically
the question is: when have I done the act of גניבה? geneiva?
Because if it died before I've done the act of גניבה, geneiva,
I don't have to pay you for it. If it died after
I've done the act of גניבה, geneiva, then I'm already obligated to
pay you because from the moment I stole it. So if it's
ומת ברשות בעלים, u'meis b'reshous ba'alin, if it died while it was
still in your property פטור, patur, exempt. הגביהו, higbi'o, if I picked
it up okay, it was not a cow, it's a sheep if
I picked it up, או שהוציאו, o shehotzio, or I walked it
out, מרשות בעלים ומת me'reshous ba'alin u'meis חייב. chayav. And died, then
I'm חייב. chayav. Okay? So that's basically the question of: you need
to do the act of גניבה geneiva is when you go ahead
and take possession of it. So what's the debate here?
Did it just die in natural causes? גניבה geneiva mean like throw
it in the No, no. Natural causes. Then you'd be חייב chayav
for theft.
Correct. Yeah. רבינא דייק מרישא, Ravina deyiek me'reisha, רב אחא דייק מסיפא.
Rav Acha deyiek me'seifa.
So רבינא Ravina is focuses on, like, derives from the language of
the beginning, and רב אחא Rav Acha from the language at the
end. רבינא דייק מרישא: Ravina deyiek me'reisha: היה מושכו ויוצא ומת ברשות
בעלים. haya moshcho ve'yotze u'meis b'reshous ba'alin. If it died in the
owner's domain פטור, patur, you're exempt. טעמא דמת ברשות בעלים. ta'ama d'meis
b'reshous ba'alin. The only reason you're exempt is that it died in
the owner's domain. הא הוציאו מרשות בעלים, ha hotzio me'reshous ba'alin,
as soon as you took it out of their domain, ומת u'meis
חייב. chayav. You'd be חייב chayav even if you took it into
רשות הרבים. reshous harabbim. The emphasis here is: you're פטור patur while
it's still in the owner's domain. As soon as you step it
out of the owner's domain, I don't care where you bring it
into, you're חייב. chayav. Okay, which is a very reasonable read. רב
אחא דייק מסיפא. Rav Acha deyiek me'seifa. רב
אחא Rav Acha focuses on the end. הגביהו או שהוציאו, higbi'o o
shehotzio, if you lifted it up or took it out. הוצאה דומיא
דהגבהה. hotza'ah dumiya d'hagba'ah. So it's comparing taking it out to similar
to an act of הגבהה. hagba'ah. מה הגבהה דאתיא לרשותיה, mah hagba'ah
d'asyei l'reshusei,
the same way הגבהה hagba'ah means that you take it fully into
your control, אף הוצאה נמי דאתיא לרשותיה. af hotza'ah nami d'asyei l'reshusei.
So taking it out of the owner's domain has to be into
your control. And therefore, it's only going to be חייב chayav if
you do bring it into a סימטא simta or רשות היחיד, reshous
hayachid, but not into רשות הרבים. reshous harabbim. It's not enough to
take it out of their domain; you have to bring it into
your control. Now, I want to just pause for a moment and
say: are they arguing in general whether to be קונה koneh an
object? Can I be קונה koneh something by dragging it to רשות
הרבים? reshous harabbim? Does not seem so. It would seem that logically,
I mean throughout all of ש"ס Shas we assume that the only
way I can be קונה koneh an object is, you know, without
הגבהה, hagba'ah, is by bringing it into some space where I've got
some some control over it; that I can't be קונה koneh objects
in רשות הרבים reshous harabbim without הגבהה hagba'ah or יד. yad. Okay?
So it does not seem like they're arguing the general question of
can you be קונה koneh something in רשות הרבים. reshous harabbim. It
seems like they're arguing the specific question of being חייב chayav as
a גנב. ganav. What do you need to do an act of
גניבה? geneiva? We've been assuming until this minute that an act of
גניבה geneiva requires the same act as an act of קנין. kinyan.
But maybe not. From your perspective you, the victim you don't care
whether I've taken it into my possession; you just care that I've
taken it out of your possession. So maybe an act of גניבה
geneiva is enough that I've removed it from your domain even if
I haven't done the normal type of act that would bring it
into my domain. Okay? So then the other position says: no, even
for an act of גניבה, geneiva, it has to be like a
normal act of קנין; kinyan; you have to bring it into your
control as well. So the nice way of understanding this debate is
not a debate about קנין kinyan קנין kinyan would never happen going
from רשות היחיד reshous hayachid to רשות הרבים reshous harabbim unless I
do הגבהה hagba'ah or put it in my יד? yad? No,
I already said not that. Okay. But but this is a debate
of of גניבה: geneiva: that is the act of גניבה geneiva like
an act of קנין kinyan and you have to take it out
of one person's control and bring it into yours, or is the
act of גניבה geneiva enough to take it out of the other
person's control? And if you say that, then then it's a perfect
read of the ברייתא. braisa. I'm dragging it out of your רשות,
reshous, I bring it into רשות הרבים, reshous harabbim, I'm חייב. chayav.
Why did I do גניבה? geneiva? 'Cause I took it out of
your רשות. reshous. I don't have to bring it into mine. As
long as I took it out of your רשות, reshous, I'm חייב.
chayav. And the moment I take it out of your רשות, reshous,
I both do חילול שבת chillul Shabbos and גניבה geneiva at the
same time. So now the גמרא Gemara just wraps this up. The
גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, ולרב אחא קשיא רישא ולרבינא קשיא
סיפא. u'le'Rav Acha kashya reisha, u'le'Ravina kashya seifa.
How do they deal with the דיוקים diyukim of the opposite דיוקים?
diyukim? So the גמרא Gemara says: רישא לרב אחא לא קשיא, reisha
le'Rav Acha lo kashya, the beginning is not difficult for רב אחא.
Rav Acha. כמה דלא אתיא לרשותיה רשות בעלים קרינא ביה. kama d'lo
asyei l'reshusei, reshous ba'alin karinan beih. When it says "if you took
it out of the owner's domain," I'm going to say as long
as you haven't taken it into your domain, it's not considered like
you took it out of his domain. So you want to say
as soon as you take it out of domain you're חייב; chayav;
I say no, you have to take it into yours. And what
and the point is that as long as it's not in yours,
it's like it's still in his. Okay. רבינא קרינא ביה. Ravina karina
beih. סיפא
לרבינא לא קשיא. Seifa leravina lo kashya. And the end that it
compares הגבהה hagbah to הוצאה hotza'ah is not difficult to Ravina. הוצאה
דומיא דהגבהה לא אמרינן. Hotza'ah dumiya dehagbah lo aminan. No, I don't
make that comparison. When you lift it up it's one way to
steal it, even if you're in the guy's domain. But when you
take it out, it doesn't have to be a normal קנין. kinyan.
The moment you take it out, that's גניבה gneivah even if it's
not a normal קנין, kinyan, even if it's not taking it into
your domain. Okay, so let's go. We have two more minutes. Let's
finish the דף. daf. Five more minutes. Okay. Alright, so very good.
So I should want to point out that was a major סוגיא
sugaya about קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kimlei bidrabei minei, one of the
major סוגיאs sugaya in ש"ס. Shas. I also want to point out
that it was all a construction of the סתם. stam. Okay, there
was like almost everything was weaving in statements that other people had
said in other contexts. You might have noticed there was
no like אביי Abbaye says this, רבא Rava says that or whatever.
It's just a whole big סוגיא sugaya created by the סתם stam
about the idea of קים ליה kimlei and about things coming at
the same time or at different times. Okay, and what's considered one
process or not. Okay. So let's just read.
The phrase קים ליה kimlei was never used.
The phrase קים ליה kimlei was never used. Interesting. But now we're
going to get onto another aspect of קים ליה kimlei and let's
just at least get started with it. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says הבא על אחותו ועל אחות אביו. Habah al achoto ve'al achot
aviv. If somebody has sex with his sister or his father's sister,
so that's an איסור כרת. issur kares. And even though it's an
איסור כרת, issur kares, you still pay the קנס knas because it's
a... we don't say that it has to be a woman that
it's possible to marry. But now the גמרא Gemara says we're going
to be back at our קים ליה kimlei question. Okay. And it's
one thing to say, okay, only before we said you need to
be a חייב מיתה chayav misa to override a monetary payment. But
here the גמרא Gemara is going to say but one minute, how
about the fact that this person is deserving of lashes? Wouldn't that
also override a monetary payment? That's not a punishment up in heaven,
right? That's actually a real punishment down here. So the גמרא Gemara
says רמינהו, reminu, I'll ask you on this. אלו הן הלוקים. Elu
hen halokim. The following people get lashes. הבא על אחותו, Habah al
achoto, man who has sex with his sister, ועל אחות אביו ועל
אחות אמו ועל אחות אשתו, ve'al achot aviv, ve'al achot imo, ve'al
achot ishto, or father or mother's sister or his wife's sister, ועל
אשת אחיו, ve'al eshet achiv, or his brother's wife, ועל אשת אחי
אביו, ve'al eshet achi aviv, or his uncle's wife, ועל הנידה. ve'al
haniddah. Okay. And with a woman who is a נידה. niddah. וקיימא
לן, Vekayma lan, and we have a principle, דאינו לוקה ומשלם, de'eino
lokeh umishalem, that a person doesn't both get lashes and pay. So
if these acts of כרת kares within the case of the משנה
Mishnah are deserving of lashes, תוספות Tosafot points out even the act
of having sex with a ממזר mamzer for example would be deserving
of lashes, then why is it saying that you pay the fine?
Now, one thing to understand here is all the cases before we
didn't actually get the punishment in the court. You just did a
sin that was deserving of כרת, kares, deserving of מיתה. misa. The
principle אינו לוקה ומשלם eino lokeh umishalem tends to be more of
a principle that when you actually get lashes administered, we're not going
to actually make you also pay. But you understand the difference. One
is just it's the weighty enough sin that I would be deserving
of כרת kares or מיתה misa even if the court doesn't know
about it. This is a case where actually the simple sense אינו
לוקה ומשלם eino lokeh umishalem speaks about you don't actually get lashes
and pay. If we're actually administering the lashes, you're not going to
pay. But the גמרא, Gemara, so anyway, we'll get to that. But
the גמרא Gemara wants to know... bam! Sorry. Shoot.
Pick that up later. Let's just read to the end of the
דף. daf. Have to cut that out of the audio. So the
גמרא Gemara wants to know,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so the גמרא Gemara says,
so why is it therefore the גמרא Gemara says that you'll pay
the קנס, knas, that you'll pay the fine? Isn't it a case
that you'll get lashes? Okay. Now the simple answer would be they
didn't give you warning, they didn't... there weren't witnesses, you're not going
to get lashes. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר
עולא לא קשיא. Amar Ulla lo kashya. כאן באחותו נערה Kan be'achoto
na... You know what, let's end here. Okay, because I got to
clean up this mess and we got to go to דאווענינג. davening.
So we will pick up with this tomorrow. No, just
a fantastic way you define גניבה gneivah from this perspective. Thank you.
Oh wow, very nice, thanks. Yeah, David, be careful. You
might want to go around the other way, too late for that.